the same machines in a different mode, and in that mode, you could make microscopic blood flow movies from hundreds of thousands of sites independently in the brain. Okay, so what? In fact, the so what is, in the brain, changes in neural activity, the things that make your brain work, the things that make your software work in your brain, are tightly correlated with changes in blood flow. You make a blood flow movie, you have an independent proxy of brain activity. This has literally revolutionized cognitive science. Take any cognitive domain you want, memory, motor planning, thinking about your mother-in-law, getting angry at people, emotional response, it goes on and on, put people into functional MRI devices, and image how these kinds of variables map onto brain activity. It's in its early stages, and it's crude by some measures, but in fact, 20 years ago, we were at nothing. You couldn't do people like this. You couldn't do healthy people. That's caused a literal revolution, and it's opened us up to a new experimental preparation. Neurobiologists, as you well know, have lots of experimental preps, worms and rodents and fruit flies and things like this. And now, we have a new experimental prep: human beings. We can now use human beings to study and model the software in human beings, and we have a few burgeoning biological measures. Okay, let me give you one example of the kinds of experiments that people do, and it's in the area of what you'd call valuation. Valuation is just what you think it is, you know? If you went and you were valuing two companies against one another, you'd want to know which was more valuable. Cultures discovered the key feature of valuation thousands of years ago. If you want to compare oranges to windshields, what do you do? Well, you can't compare oranges to windshields. They're immiscible. They don't mix with one another. So instead, you convert them to a common currency scale, put them on that scale, and value them accordingly. Well, your brain has to do something just like that as well, and we're now beginning to understand and identify brain systems involved in valuation, and one of them includes a neurotransmitter system whose cells are located in your brainstem and deliver the chemical dopamine to the rest of your brain. I won't go through the details of it, but that's an important discovery, and we know a good bit about that now, and it's just a small piece of it, but it's important because those are the neurons that you would lose if you had Parkinson's disease, and they're also the neurons that are hijacked by literally every drug of abuse, and that makes sense. Drugs of abuse would come in, and they would change the way you value the world. They change the way you value the symbols associated with your drug of choice, and they make you value that over everything else. Here's the key feature though. These neurons are also involved in the way you can assign value to literally abstract ideas, and I put some symbols up here that we assign value to for various reasons. We have a behavioral superpower in our brain, and it at least in part involves dopamine. We can deny every instinct we have for survival for an idea, for a mere idea. No other species can do that. In 1997, the cult Heaven's Gate committed mass suicide predicated on the idea that there was a spaceship hiding in the tail of the then-visible comet Hale-Bopp waiting to take them to the next level. It was an incredibly tragic event. More than two thirds of them had college degrees. But the point here is they were able to deny their instincts for survival using exactly the same systems that were put there to make them survive. That's a lot of control, okay? One thing that I've left out of this narrative is the obvious thing, which is the focus of the rest of my little talk, and that is other people. These same valuation systems are redeployed when we're valuing interactions with other people. So this same dopamine system that gets addicted to drugs, that makes you freeze when you get Parkinson's disease, that contributes to various forms of psychosis, is also redeployed to value interactions with other people and to assign value to gestures that you do when you're interacting with somebody else. Let me give you an example of this. You bring to the table such enormous processing power in this domain that you hardly even notice it. Let me just give you a few examples. So here's a baby. She's three months old. She still poops in her diapers and she can't do calculus. She's related to me. Somebody will be very glad that she's up here on the screen. You can cover up one of her eyes, and you can still read something in the other eye, and I see sort of curiosity in one eye, I see maybe a little bit of surprise in the other. Here's a couple. They're sharing a moment together, and we've even done an experiment where you can cut out different pieces of this frame and you can still see that they're sharing it. They're sharing it sort of in parallel. Now, the elements of the scene also communicate this to us, but you can read it straight off their faces, and if you compare their faces to normal faces, it would be a very subtle cue. Here's another couple. He's projecting out at us, and she's clearly projecting, you know, love and admiration at him. Here's another couple. (Laughter) And I'm thinking I'm not seeing love and admiration on the left. (Laughter) In fact, I know this is his sister, and you can just see him saying, "Okay, we're doing this for the camera, and then afterwards you steal my candy and you punch me in the face." (Laughter) He'll kill me for showing that. All right, so what does this mean? It means we bring an enormous amount of processing power to the problem. It engages deep systems in our brain, in dopaminergic systems that are there to make you chase sex, food and salt. They keep you alive. It gives them the pie, it gives that kind of a behavioral punch which we've called a superpower. So how can we take that and arrange a kind of staged social interaction and turn that into a scientific probe? And the short answer is games. Economic games. So what we do is we go into two areas. One area is called experimental economics. The other area is called behavioral economics. And we steal their games. And we contrive them to our own purposes. So this shows you one particular game called an ultimatum game. Red person is given a hundred dollars and can offer a split to blue. Let's say red wants to keep 70, and offers blue 30. So he offers a 70-30 split with blue. Control passes to blue, and blue says, "I accept it," in which case he'd get the money, or blue says, "I reject it," in which case no one gets anything. Okay? So a rational choice economist would say, well, you should take all non-zero offers. What do people do? People are indifferent at an 80-20 split. At 80-20, it's a coin flip whether you accept that or not. Why is that? You know, because you're pissed off. You're mad. That's an unfair offer, and you know what an unfair offer is. This is the kind of game done by my lab and many around the world. That just gives you an example of the kind of thing that these games probe. The interesting thing is, these games require that you have a lot of cognitive apparatus on line. You have to be able to come to the table with a proper model of another person. You have to be able to remember what you've done. You have to stand up in the moment to do that. Then you have to update your model based on the signals coming back, and you have to do something that is interesting, which is you have to do a kind of depth of thought assay. That is, you have to decide what that other person expects of you. You have to send signals to manage your image in their mind. Like a job interview. You sit across the desk from somebody, they have some prior image of you, you send signals across the desk to move their image of you from one place to a place where you want it to be. We're so good at this we don't really even notice it. These kinds of probes exploit it. Okay? In doing this, what we've discovered is that humans are literal canaries in social exchanges. Canaries used to be used as kind of biosensors in mines. When methane built up, or carbon dioxide built up, or oxygen was diminished, the birds would swoon before people would -- so it acted as an early warning system: Hey, get out of the mine. Things aren't going so well. People come to the table, and even these very blunt, staged social interactions, and they, and there's just numbers going back and forth between the people, and they bring enormous sensitivities to it. So we realized we could exploit this, and in fact, as we've done that, and we've done this now in many thousands of people, I think on the order of five or six thousand. We actually, to make this a biological probe, need bigger numbers than that, remarkably so. But anyway, patterns have emerged, and we've been able to take those patterns, convert them into mathematical models, and use those mathematical models to gain new insights into these exchanges. Okay, so what? Well, the so what is, that's a really nice behavioral measure, the economic games bring to us notions of optimal play. We can compute that during the game. And we can use that to sort of carve up the behavior. Here's the cool thing. Six or seven years ago, we developed a team. It was at the time in Houston, Texas. It's now in Virginia and London. And we built software that'll link functional magnetic resonance imaging devices up over the Internet. I guess we've done up to six machines at a time, but let's just focus on two. So it synchronizes machines anywhere in the world. We synchronize the machines, set them into these staged social interactions, and we eavesdrop on both of the interacting brains. So for the first time, we don't have to look at just averages over single individuals, or have individuals playing computers, or try to make inferences that way. We can study individual dyads. We can study the way that one person interacts with another person, turn the numbers up, and start to gain new insights into the boundaries of normal cognition, but more importantly, we can put people with classically defined mental illnesses, or brain damage, into these social interactions, and use these as probes of that. So we've started this effort. We've made a few hits, a few, I think, embryonic discoveries. We think there's a future to this. But it's our way of going in and redefining, with a new lexicon, a mathematical one actually, as opposed to the standard ways that we think about mental illness, characterizing these diseases, by using the people as birds in the exchanges. That is, we exploit the fact that the healthy partner, playing somebody with major depression, or playing somebody with autism spectrum disorder, or playing somebody with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, we use that as a kind of biosensor, and then we use computer programs to model that person, and it gives us a kind of assay of this. Early days, and we're just beginning, we're setting up sites around the world. Here are a few of our collaborating sites. The hub, ironically enough, is centered in little Roanoke, Virginia. There's another hub in London, now, and the rest are getting set up. We hope to give the data away at some stage. That's a complicated issue about making it available to the rest of the world. But we're also studying just a small part of what makes us interesting as human beings, and so I would invite other people who are interested in this to ask us for the software, or even for guidance on how to move forward with that. Let me leave you with one thought in closing. The interesting thing about studying cognition has been that we've been limited, in a way. We just haven't had the tools to look at interacting brains simultaneously. The fact is, though, that even when we're alone, we're a profoundly social creature. We're not a solitary mind built out of properties that kept it alive in the world independent of other people. In fact, our minds depend on other people. They depend on other people, and they're expressed in other people, so the notion of who you are, you often don't know who you are until you see yourself in interaction with people that are close to you, people that are enemies of you, people that are agnostic to you. So this is the first sort of step into using that insight into what makes us human beings, turning it into a tool, and trying to gain new insights into mental illness. Thanks for having me. (Applause) (Applause)
estas máquinas de manera diferente, y por lo tanto, podemos hacer videos del flujo sanguíneo microscópico de miles de sitios independientes en el cerebro. Bueno, ¿y eso qué tiene que ver? Pues que los cambios en la actividad neural, las cosas que hacen que tu cerebro funcione, las cosas que hacen que el software de tu cerebro trabaje, están completamente correlacionadas con los cambios de flujo sanguíneo. Si haces un video del flujo sanguíneo, tienes una representación independiente de actividad cerebral. Esto literalmente ha revolucionado a la ciencia cognitiva. No importa el área cognitiva, sea la memoria, la planificación motora, pensar acerca de tu suegra, molestarse con alguien, una reacción emocional, la lista es infinita, pongan a alguien dentro de una máquina de imágenes por resonancia magnética funcional, e imaginen cómo estas variables mapean la actividad cerebral. Aún está en una etapa inicial, y es rudimentaria en cierto modo, pero de hecho, hace 20 años, no estábamos en nada. No se podía examinar a la gente de esta manera. No se podían examinar a personas sanas. Eso ha causado una revolución que nos ha llevado a una preparación experimental nueva. Los neurobiólogos, como bien saben, experimentan con una gran cantidad de animales, lombrices y roedores y moscas de la fruta y cosas así. Y ahora, tenemos un nuevo objeto de estudio: los seres humanos. Ahora podemos usar a los seres humanos para estudiar y hacer modelos del software en los seres humanos, y tenemos algunas medidas biológicas prometedoras. Muy bien, déjenme darles un ejemplo de la clase de experimentos que se hacen, y es en el área conocida como valoración. Valoración es justo lo que están pensando, ¿muy bien? Si vas a valorar dos compañías entre sí, lo que necesitas saber es cuál es más valiosa. Las culturas descubrieron el factor clave de la valoración hace miles de años. Si quieres comparar naranjas con parabrisas, ¿qué tienes que hacer? Bueno, uno no puede comparar naranjas con parabrisas. Son objetos no miscibles. No se mezclan entre sí. Por lo tanto, hay que pasarlos a una escala monetaria común, ponerlos en tal escala, y valorarlos de acuerdo a esta. Pues tu cerebro tiene que hacer algo parecido también, y ahora estamos comenzando a entender e identificar los sistemas cerebrales ligados a la valoración, y uno de ellos posee un sistema neurotransmisor cuyas células están localizadas en el tronco del encéfalo y que le suministran dopamina al resto de tu cerebro. No entraré en detalle, pero este es un descubrimiento importante, y ahora sabemos un poco acerca de este proceso, y es tan solo una pequeña parte, pero es importante porque esas son las neuronas que perderías si tuvieras mal de Parkinson, y son también las neuronas que son atacadas literalmente por todo estupefaciente, y eso tiene mucho sentido. Los estupefacientes entran y cambian la manera en que valoras el mundo. Cambian la manera en que valoras los símbolos asociados con tu droga preferida, y te hacen valorar eso sobre todo lo demás. Aquí está la parte clave. Estas neuronas también están involucradas en la manera en que tú le das valor a ideas abstractas, y acá puse algunos símbolos a los que les asignamos valor por varias razones. Nosotros tenemos un superpoder de conducta en nuestro cerebro, que en parte utiliza dopamina. Nosotros podemos ignorar todos nuestros instintos de supervivencia por una idea, por una mera idea. Ninguna otra especie puede hacer eso. En 1997, la secta Heaven's Gate cometió un suicidio en masa basado en la idea de que había una nave espacial escondida en la cola del en ese entonces visible cometa Hale-Bopp que los llevaría a otro mundo. Fue un evento increíblemente trágico. Más de dos tercios de ellos tenían títulos universitarios. Pero el punto importante acá es que ellos fueron capaces de ignorar sus instintos de supervivencia usando exactamente los mismos sistemas que fueron puestos para que sobrevivieran. Eso es un gran nivel de control, ¿muy bien? Una cosa que he omitido de esta narrativa es lo obvio, que es el tema central del resto de mi breve charla, y es nada menos que las otras personas. Estos mismos sistemas de valoración son desplegados cuando estamos valorando las interacciones con otras personas. Entonces este mismo sistema de dopamina que nos vuelve adictos a las drogas, que hace que te petrifiques cuando tienes mal de Parkinson, que contribuye a varias formas de psicosis, es también desplegado para valorar las interacciones con otras personas y asignarle valor a los gestos que haces cuando estás interactuando con otra persona. Déjenme darles un ejemplo de lo anterior. La cantidad de poder de procesamiento que tú despliegas en esta área es enorme y ni siquiera te das cuenta. Déjenme darle algunos ejemplos. Acá vemos a una bebé. Ella tiene tres meses de edad. Aún se hace popó en los pañales y no puede hacer cálculos matemáticos. Es familiar mía. Alguien está muy feliz de que ella haya salido en esta pantalla. Uno puede cubrir uno de sus ojos, y seguir viendo algo en el otro ojo, y yo veo curiosidad en un ojo, y quizás un poco de sorpresa en el otro. Acá tenemos a una pareja. Ellos están compartiendo un momento, e incluso hemos hecho un experimento cortando las partes de este cuadro, y uno aún puede ver que ellos están compartiendo el momento más o menos en paralelo. Los elementos de la foto también nos comunican eso, pero puedes verlo sin duda alguna en sus caras, y si comparas sus caras con otras normales, las pistas serían muy sutiles. Esta es otra pareja. Él se está proyectando hacia nosotros, y ella claramente proyecta, ustedes saben, amor y admiración hacia él. Esta es otra pareja. (Risas) Y creo que no hay amor o admiración viniendo del lado izquierdo. (Risas) De hecho, yo sé que ella es su hermana, y uno puede adivinar lo que él está pensando, "Muy bien, solo estamos juntos porque posamos para la cámara, pero luego te robarás mis dulces y me golpearás en la cara". (Risas) Él me va a matar por haber mostrado esto. Muy bien, ¿entonces esto qué significa? Significa que nosotros desplegamos una enorme cantidad de poder de procesamiento en cada problema. Conecta sistemas en el fondo de nuestro cerebro, en sistemas dopaminérgicos que están ahí para que busques sexo, comida y sal. Te mantienen vivo. Les da el empuje, les da el tipo de poder de conducta al que hemos llamado superpoder. ¿Entonces cómo podemos tomar eso y montar una especie de interacción social simulada y convertirla en una indagación científica? Y la respuesta corta es, con juegos. Juegos de economía. Lo que hacemos entonces es tocar dos áreas. Un área la llamamos economía experimental. La otra es llamada economía conductual. Les robamos los juegos y los manipulamos para nuestros propios fines. Acá vemos uno en particular llamado el juego del ultimátum. A la persona de rojo se le dan 100 dólares que los puede compartir con la persona de azul. Digamos que el de rojo quiere quedarse con 70, y le ofrece 30 al de azul. Entonces él ofrece una partición de 70-30 al de azul. El control se le pasa al de azul, quien dice, "acepto," y en este caso recibiría el dinero. O el de azul dice, "lo rechazo," y en este caso nadie recibe nada. ¿Está bien? Pues una decisión racional, dirían los economistas, sería tomar todas las propuestas que no sean nulas. ¿Qué hace la gente? La gente es indiferente a la partición 80-20. En 80-20, se lanza una moneda así aceptes o no. ¿Por qué? Porque tienes rabia. Estás molesto. Es una oferta injusta, y tú sabes lo que es una oferta injusta. Este es el tipo de juego que se hace en mi laboratorio y en muchos otros alrededor del mundo. Les da un ejemplo de la clase de cosas que estos juegos indagan. Lo interesante es que estos juegos requieren que tú tengas un gran aparato cognitivo en ese momento. Tienes que ser capaz de posicionarte con un modelo adecuado de la otra persona, tienes que ser capaz de recordar lo que haz hecho, tienes que estar de pie en ese momento para poder hacerlo, luego tienes que actualizar tu modelo basándote en las señales que te están llegando, y tienes que hacer algo que es muy interesante, y es que tienes que hacer una especie de evaluación. O sea, tienes que decidir lo que la otra persona está esperando de ti. Tienes que enviar señales para manipular tu imagen en la mente de ellos. Como una entrevista de trabajo. Te sientas en frente del escritorio de alguien, ese alguien tiene una imagen previa tuya, tú le envías señales para que perciba la imagen que tú quieres proyectar. Somos tan buenos para eso que ni siquiera nos damos cuenta. Este tipo de indagaciones intensifican ese proceso. ¿Muy bien? Al hacer esto hemos descubierto que los seres humanos son como canarios en momentos de intercambio social. Los canarios eran usados como biosensores en las minas. Cuando los niveles de metano o de dióxido de carbono se acumulaban, o si el oxígeno disminuía, los pájaros eran los primeros en desmayarse, y por lo tanto servían como un sistema de aviso: Eh, salgan de la mina. Esto va para mal. Las personas vienen a estos juegos, y aunque estas toscas interacciones sociales sean montadas, y lo son, y tan solo sean números que se intercambian entre los participantes, las personas despliegan una gran sensibilidad. Entonces nos dimos cuenta que podíamos aprovecharnos de esto, y en realidad, mientras lo hemos hecho, y lo hemos hecho en miles de personas, creo que más o menos a unas cinco o seis mil personas. De hecho, para hacer tal indagación biológica, necesitamos un número mayor, mucho mayor. De todas maneras hay patrones que han salido a flote, y hemos podido tomar esos patrones, convertirlos en modelos matemáticos, y usarlos para tener nuevos puntos de vista acerca de estos intercambios. Bueno, ¿y esto qué importancia tiene? Lo importante es que es una medida de conducta clara, los juegos de economía nos dan claves de juego óptimo, podemos computarlas durante el juego, y podemos usarlas para moldear el comportamiento en cierto grado. He aquí lo estupendo. Hace seis o siete años creamos un equipo. En ese momento se reunía en Houston, Texas. Hoy se reúne en Virginia y en Londres. Y construímos un software que permite conectar los aparatos de imágenes por resonancia magnética funcional a internet. Creo que ya hemos conectado unas seis máquinas, pero enfoquémonos en estas dos. Entonces sincroniza máquinas en cualquier lugar del mundo, nosotros sincronizamos las máquinas, las preparamos para las interacciones sociales simuladas, y monitoreamos cada uno de los cerebros que están interactuando. Y por vez primera, no necesitamos enfocarnos en los promedios de los participantes, o de ponerlos a jugar en la computadora, o tratar de llegar a inferencias de esa manera. Podemos estudiar díadas por separado. Podemos estudiar la manera en que una persona interactúa con otra persona, desplegar los datos, y obtener una mejor comprensión acerca de los parámetros de cognición normal. Pero más importante aún, es que podemos poner a personas con enfermedades mentales específicas, o con daño cerebral, en estas interacciones sociales y usarlas para generar investigaciones. Nos hemos dedicado entonces a esta labor y creo que hemos obtenido, aunque sean pocos, algunos descubrimientos embriónicos. Creemos que hay un futuro en esto. Pero es nuestra manera de ir redefiniendo, con un nuevo léxico, y uno matemático para ser preciso, a comparación de la manera tradicional en que describimos las enfermedades mentales, caracterizando estas enfermedades usando a las personas como canarios en estos intercambios. O sea, aprovechamos que un participante sano jugando con otro que sufre de depresión, o jugando con alguien que padezca de trastorno del espectro autista, o con alguien que posea trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad, nos sirva como una especie de biosensor, y luego utilizamos programas de computadora para modelar a esa persona, obteniendo así una evaluación de esto. Son las primeras etapas, pero estamos estableciendo sitios alrededor del mundo. Acá pueden ver algunos de nuestros sitios de colaboración. Su centro, irónicamente, está localizado en la pequeña Roanoke, Virginia. Hay otro centro en Londres en este momento, y el resto están en desarrollo. Esperamos revelar los datos en determinado momento. Hacerlos accesibles al resto del mundo es un tema complejo. Pero también estamos estudiando una pequeña parte de lo que nos hace interesantes a los seres humanos, y quiero invitar a las personas que estén interesadas en esto para preguntarnos por el software, o para una orientación de cómo seguir adelante con esto. Permítanme dejarlos con un reflexión para concluir. Lo interesante acerca del estudio de la cognición es que hemos estado limitados en cierto modo. Simplemente no hemos tenido las herramientas para estudiar cerebros interactuando simultáneamente. La realidad, sin embargo, es que incluso cuando estamos solos, somos criaturas completamente sociales. No somos una mente solitaria construida mediante propiedades que la mantienen viva en el mundo independiente de otras personas. De hecho, nuestras mentes dependen de otras personas. Ellas dependen de otras personas, y son expresadas en otras personas, entonces la noción de lo que tú eres, solo te es clara justo en el momento en el que te ves interactuando con otras personas cercanas a ti, personas que sean enemigas tuyas, personas que te vean con reserva. Entonces este primer bosquejo nos permite entender lo que nos hace humanos, convertirlo en una herramienta, y generar nuevas perspectivas acerca de las enfermedades mentales. Gracias por invitarme. (Aplausos) (Aplausos)